Guide to the James Lippincott Goodwin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Carthage Plantation Correspondence, 1927-1959; Series IV
  - Dowd Piece, 1927-1930 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and lawyer P. P. Pelton regarding purchase of this 20 acres of property in Carthage, 1927 and the second purchase of 187 acres of Dowd property in 1930.
  - Fire and Fire Protection, 1927-1942 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    1927 correspondence between W. C. McCormick, Assistant State Forester, Department of Conservation and Development including 1928 Cooperative Agreement for the protection of lands from forest fires and state distribution of trees for forest planting; 1930 correspondence between James L. Goodwin, regarding inefficient suppression of fire on Carthage property by Forest Fire Warden Organization; 1941 payment by Colonel Benjamin L. Jacobson, Finance Department of First Army, for injury to Goodwin Moore County property during Army maneuvers there.
  - Lang Piece, 1933-1941 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Mrs. Lang, through Colin G. Spencer, offers 453 acres of land that is adjacent to Mr. Goodwin's Carthage property in 1933. James L. Goodwin purchases 65 acres of this property in December, 1934. In January 1941 James L. Goodwin purchases 388 acres of Lang property with lawyer, M. G. Boyette doing this title search.
  - Charlie Leak, North Carolina, 1933-1938 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Charlie Leak, a handyman, employed to care for Carthage property of Mr. Goodwin's secures loans from Mr. Goodwin and gives him mortgage to his property, Attorney W. D. Sabiston, Jr., investigating Mr. Leak's title to twelve acres in Carthage but Mr. Goodwin does not take title.
  - Maps and Studies of Growth Timber, 1928-1952 (Box 14, Folder 7a)
    Maps of the Sears property, 1942; Timber Cruise, 1952; Carthage Map by J. Atwood Whitman, Consulting Forester.
  - Miscellaneous Road Improvements, 1928-1942 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    1930 Disbursement sheets, Statements of material and labor used on Carthage property; 1935 Building costs for new road across land purchased from Lang; Cleaning and maintenance of property; 1937 Labor costs of Charles Leak and Paul Lamm; 1938 Itemized report of labor; 1939 Disbursements for work done on house, carpenter, report of labor; roofing and reshingling; 1928-1942 Communication between Colin Spencer and James L. Goodwin about costs and process of road improvement.
  - North Carolina Forestry Association, 1943-1965 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    1943-1965 Receipts and membership cards for J. L. Goodwin; 1957 List of consulting foresters; 1958 Governor's Conference on Small Woodland Management.
  - Plantation, 1928-1942 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    1928 Spencer correspondence contending that Loblolly pine is superior to shortleaf pine; 1935 Spencer report on the satisfactory condition of the plantation including milling, lumber, planting redbud and flowering peach trees and shipping pulpwood; 1941 Disbursement sheets from Mr. Spencer to Mr. Goodwin and Roger D. Huff report of Carthage property and suggested selective cutting of trees; 1942 Report on wood cut, property improvement and labor disbursements.
  - Properties: Carthage and other Moore County Properties offered by sale, 1927-1942 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    927 James L. Goodwin to Dr. Eli Long proposing a joint ownership and club arrangement for some Spencer land; 1931 Offers of land by Edward J. Burns and Annette Barrett Dewey; 1941 Timber Cruise Report on the Britt Land; 1941 James L. Goodwin takes first mortgage on J. C. Hammond place.
  - Property: Carthage, 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    1944 Correspondence between James L. Goodwin, H. H. Chapman, Yale Forestry School and Colin Spencer regarding H. H. Chapman criticism of certain Spencer forestry practices on Goodwin Carthage land; 1945 Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and J. A. Gibb, Chief, Regional Forestry Division, United States Department of Agriculture, Soil Conservation Service, regarding Mr. Goodwin's statement of the history of his Carthage property from the purchase in 1927 to current better forestry practices.
  - Property, North Carolina Real Estate, 1927-1934 (Box 14, Folder 12a)
    Deeds and abstracts to the Carthage Property, 1927-1930 and Chain of title to the Lang Property, 1934.
  - Purchase, North Carolina, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Correspondence with lawyer M. G. Boyette acknowledging amount of $6,000 to be paid to Mr. and Mrs. J. A. Lang for their 388 acres; Easement papers granting Randolph Electric Membership Corporation privilege of running rural electric power line through Carthage property.
  - Sears, 1930-1936 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Colin Spencer in 1930 evincing initial interest in this 141 acre Sears tract; Lawyers P. P. Pelton and Roger Davis investigating title; and in 1931 Mr. Goodwin taking title to Sears property; 1932, 1934, 1935 Disbursement sheets of Sears property.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin giving disbursements for labor maintenance of property such as roads built, trees planted, cutting and lumber manufacture; Purchase of timber from Mr. Goodwin by Mr. Spencer.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin regarding the Carthage property including a list of wages paid for operation of property; stocking wild turkeys given free by North Carolina on property; refusal of request by Army maneuvers on the property because Mr. Goodwin feels the property's conservation value may be injured; Roger D. Huff investigating and making a sample area of selective cutting; Building connecting roads.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin regarding Mr. Spencer's securing a loan to purchase property; Mr. Goodwin's letter of opposition to proposed North Carolina legislation of state regulation and control of timber cuttings on private land, this letter read to North Carolina Association Foresters by its President, Colin G. Spencer; Life Magazine essay on forestry using Carthage illustrations; Booklet by Spencer "A Practical Forest Farm".
  - Spencer, Colin G., 1947-1949 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin including: Statement of Carthage Forestry and Recreation, 1947; Reports of maintenance of the property at Carthage; H. H. Chapmann correspondence concerning criticism of Mr. Spencer's forestry practices; George G. Marr, Division of Forestry, West Virginia University; correspondence acknowledging thanks for class trip to Carthage plantation; 1949 itemized disbursement list of lumber cut, wages paid and equipment used.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Correspondence, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin including statements of Carthage Capital, Forestry, Recreation; reports of forest fires on Lang place in April; 1950 disbursement sheets for labor, maintenance and timber cut.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin regarding such plantation affairs as the threatened Mrs. Lucy Sears' suit regarding disputed boundary rights; maintenance and account of plantation; Statement Carthage Forestry, Recreation and Capital, 1952.
  - Spencer, Colin G., 1953-1959 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    Correspondence with James L. Goodwin and Attorney Mosley G. Boyette regarding such plantation matters ass purchase of the McLeod tract; 1953 Establishment of Carthage plantation as 75th Tree Farm in the state; Maintenance and accounts worksheets; 1954 Timber cruise and survey by J. Atwood Whitman, Consulting Forester; 1955 Statement of work done at Carthage; 1956 Letter of acknowledged thanks for field trip to Carthage with photographs of students from Professor T. E. Maki, Forest Management, North Carolina State College; 1957 Statement of the amount of work done on the plantation for the year; 1958 lumber received by Mr. Spencer from Carthage and labor hours itemized in maintenance of plantation; North Carolina Forestry Association of Tree Farm Award to Goodwin Forest.
  - Spencer, Colin G., Jr., Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    Colin G. Spencer Jr., correspondence with James L. Goodwin regarding maintenance of Carthage plantation including payroll sheets, timber cut; Newsclipping of 50th anniversary of Mr. and Mrs. Colin G. Spencer; Dean R. J. Preston, School of Forestry, North Carolina State University letter of tribute to Colin Spencer on the event of his death in 1965.
  - Timber Cuttings, Carthage, 1946-1948 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    Listing of timber cuttings for years 1946-1948; Maps and information about exchange of land between Mr. Goodwin and Mr. Lamm.
  - Timber Estimates, 1929-1938 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    1930-1931 Reports from Harold, Sweeton in Carthage doing survey and map work; 1938 Report by Colin Spencer corrected by James L. Goodwin on Carthage history, ownership, forestry activities, planting, forest management, sent to Mr. William Maughan, Assistant, Director, Duke University, Forestry Department.
  - Timber Estimate, Carthage, 1931-1942 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    1931-Timber Volumes: Dowd South and North Tract, Sears South and North Tract, Sears South and North Tract, Lang East and West Tract; 1931-1942 Total volume of timber and cords.
  - Timber Estimate, Carthage, 1942-1943 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    1942 Estimate of Carthage timber by Harold Sweeton; 1943 Timber Cruise Report by E. H. Ward and J. D. Martin.
  - Timber Estimate, Carthage, 1942 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    Report by E. H. Ward and J. D. Martin, University of North Carolina, Timber Cruise, Carthage Plantation, December, 1942.
  - Timber Estimates, Carthage, 1952-1962 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    J. Atwood Whitman, Consulting Forester, Glendon, North Carolina employed by Colin G. Spencer to make a timber cruise and forest type map of Carthage, 1952; Mr. Whitman, in 1962 a Registered Forester with the Atlantic States Forestry Company submits 1962 report.
  - Timber Sales, 1942-1945 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    Correspondence between James L. Goodwin and Colin G. Spencer regarding the cutting and sale of hardwood and pine.
  - Timber Sales, 1945-1946 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    December, 1945-November 1946, Payroll computation, Statement of pulpwood thinning; 1946 Statement Recreation Account; December 1945-1946 Disbursement sheets for Labor Expenses.
  - Carthage, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    Directives on figuring depreciation, weeding and cutting in plantations, and closing weeding-plantation account; Tract 1 (Sears South) acreage, Tract 11 (Dowd North) acreage, Tract 111 (Lang East) acreage; Tract total volumes: pine, hardwood, cordwood.
- James L. Goodwin "Old" Correspondence, 1912-1953; Series V
  - Battell Forest, T. G. Woolsey, Jr., Paul O. Mercy, 1922-1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Map of Middlebury College and Battell Park; Preliminary Report on Battell Forest, submitted to the President, Paul D. Moody, by Theodore S. Woolsey, Jr., June 1, 1922; Paul D. Moody, President, Middlebury College, inviting James L. Goodwin to serve upon the Technical Forestry Advisory Board of Middlebury College; Management Plan for Middlebury Working Circle; Preliminary Forest Management Plan, Reserve Section Battell Forest, by J. J. Fritz, 1924; Report of Committee on Battell Forest to Board of Trustees, January 30, 1925; Memorandum relating to the Sale of Batten Forest; Report to the Board of Trustees on Proposed Sale of Battell Forest.
  - Cannon House, Chapel House, Van Durr House, Farmhouse Acquisition, 1917-1923 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Blue Prints for cottage of J. L. Goodwin; Letter to J. L. Goodwin from W. H. Burnham, Town Clerk, and Treasurer, Hampton, Connecticut relating to deeds of the Ford Property; Correspondence between Edward E. Chapel and J. L. Goodwin. Correspondence between J. L. Goodwin and Philip L. Goodwin, Architect and Brother to James L. Goodwin regarding additions to J. L. Goodwin's Farmhouse in Hampton.
  - Cedar Swamp-Reily Land, 1916-1919 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Correspondence between J. L. Goodwin, Thomas Reily and Roger Wolcott Davis, Attorney at Law, relating to J. L. Goodwin purchasing Thomas Reily property; Statement from Roger Wolcott Davis to J. L. Goodwin for professional services in re-clearing the Title land in Hampton, Connecticut.
  - Chapel House, 1944-1945 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between Stanley Galenski, Farm Employee and J. L. Goodwin with respect to rental fee for the Chapel House, and L. W. Button, Agent for Aetna Insurance Company, relating to loss of a cabin in Hampton by fire.
  - Chaplin Land, 1923-1948 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Correspondence between Roger Wolcott Davis, Attorney, and J. L. Goodwin regarding deeds of the Chaplin Property; J. L. Goodwin purchasing the Keech Cedar Swamp Lot and advising Roger Davis to search title. Taxes due on Chaplin Property for 1927; Statement pertaining to acquisitions and values to 1937; June 1943 Acreage Survey from Joseph A. Becker, Chairman, Crop Reporting Board, State of Connecticut; United States Department of Agriculture Conservation Program Application, and work-sheet including a report of performance.
  - Clark, Horace B., and Camping, 1935 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    Itemized list for camping trip from Horace B. Clark to J. L. Goodwin; L. L. Beane, Incorporated, Manufacturer of leather and Canvas Specialities, acknowledging J. L. Goodwin's order.
  - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, 1929, 1934, 1936 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    Statement pertaining to samples of corn sent by James L. Goodwin to the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station; Walter O. Filley, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, Forester, corresponding with J. L. Goodwin in regard to orders for two year seedlings and the cancellation of 5,000 two year white seedlings; Work-sheet and report of performance showing Acreage and Soil-Building Allowance.
  - Connecticut Forestry Department, Civilian Conservation Corps Camps, 1933 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    Statement from the Finance Department, United States Army, of J. L. Goodwin's Invoices for supplies furnished for Emergency Conservation work and supplies furnished for Civilian Conservation Camps; Gordon F. Chatfield, State Forest Service informing J. L. Goodwin as to transactions connected with Civilian Conservation Camps in the State of Connecticut; Correspondence between J. L. Goodwin and Austin F. Hawes, State Forester, regarding purchase of fence posts to be creosoted and sold to the State Highway Department; Notice from State Forest Service regarding obligations incurred by the State Forest Service; Goodwin purchasing fence posts from the Connecticut State Forestry Department to be resold to the State Highway Department.
  - Connecticut Land Surveyors, 1936-1949 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    Correspondence with Edwin J. Beugler, Secretary, State of Connecticut, State Board of Registration for Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors, requesting information on obtaining a license as a land surveyor; Application for registration as Land Surveyor; Rules and Regulations; Certificates of Registration issued to J. L. Goodwin from the Connecticut State Board of Registration for Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors; Booklet entitled Professional Engineers Autobiography; Harry E. Harris, The Connecticut Society of Professional Engineers, inviting J. L. Goodwin to become a member of the Society of Professional Engineers, J. L. Goodwin declining the invitation; Booklets "Code of Recommended Practice for Standard Accuracy of Maps", and "Roster of Registered Professional Engineers and Land Surveyors".
  - Cows and Dairy, 1919-1947 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    Certificates of Entry in the Herd Register of the American Jersey Cattle Club; Agreement for the Tuberculin Testing of Herds of Dairy and Breeding Cattle; Tuberculin Tested Herd Certificates to J. L. Goodwin from the United States Department of Agriculture Bureau of Animal Industry and the State of Connecticut; A. R. Merrill, Dairy Specialist, Cooperative Extension Work in Agriculture and Home Economics regarding butter making; Statements regarding cows and number, 1929; Milk Report, 1929; Quality of Milk per cow, 1930-1947; Receipts from the American Jersey Cattle Club for cost of registering cows; Ray L. Harding, Commissioner of Domestic Animals, granting permission to dispose of animals which have given a positive or suspicious reaction to test for Bang's Abortion disease; United States Department of Agriculture attempt to stop "Black Market" in live stock and meats; Statements for Operating Accounts-Cows, September and October, 1947.
  - Farmhouse Additions, 1923-1947 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    Price Proposals to J. L. Goodwin from various contractors, plumbers and his brother, Philip L. Goodwin, an Architect, with respect to radiators and boilers, wood work, windows, doors, and painters.
  - Ford House, 1927-1943 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    Correspondence regarding rentals for the Ford House and Property; Statement for upkeep, repairs, and other expenses of Ford House for years, 1923-1937; Searchings of Title, foreclosure of Ford Property purchased by Haig S. Iskiyan; Bids for repair work; Land Lord Registration Forms from the Office of Price Administration, Hartford, Connecticut; Notice to stockholders of Electric Bond and Share Company.
  - Ford House, 1927-1948 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    Haig S. Iskiyan, Appraiser and Commissare of Oriental Rugs, purchasing the Ford Property with correspondence relating to mortgage held by J. L. Goodwin; Improvements to house and property by Iskiyan; J. L. Goodwin purchasing various rugs; H. S. Iskiyan applying to the Home Owners Loan Corporation for aid in retaining possessions of homestead property; Roger Davis, Attorney, corresponding with J. L. Goodwin and H. S. Iskiyan with respect to taxes, principal of interest on mortgage owned by Iskiyan and advice to Goodwin concerning the property; Harold A. Stone, Hampton, Connecticut, purchasing a lot of the Ford Property; Mrs. Alida G. Freeman, Hampton purchasing the Ford House.
  - Forestry Practice, 1932-1933, 1959 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    T. W. Toumey, Dean of Forestry School, Yale Univeristy, urging Mr. Goodwin to continue plantations; Newell A. Norton, Research Assistant, University of Michigan, requesting forestry work.
  - Guild House, 1920-1939 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    Correspondence regarding the Right of Way for use of well by C. E. Burnham, Hampton; Roger Davis, Attorney, informing J. L. Goodwin of the purchase of the Guild House for 1922; Statement of figures for Guild House, 1923-1928, 1929-1937; List of furniture and furnishings; Statement regarding Adjustments on Sale of Guild House, August 19, 1938-James L. Goodwin to Albert R. and Amy G. Saunders; Correspondence relating to taxes on property.
  - Hampton Fire Department, (Contents Missing) (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Hampton Fire Engine and Fire Department, 1929-1933 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    Notice to Mr. and Mrs. J. L. Goodwin from Haig S. Iskiyan and James W. Cartwright of the Organization of the Fire Department and Soliciting donations for fire apparatus; Minutes of Meeting; Location for Fire House; Description of Fire Truck, "American La France".
  - Hampton Wood Fuel Coordinator, 1942 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    Governor Robert A. Hurley, Connecticut, granting permission to Austin F. Hawes, State Forester, to organize volunteers' woodlots because of fuel shortage of coal and oil; J. L. Goodwin servings as a Wood Coordinator for the town of Hampton; List of Wood Lot Owners; Notice to neighbors in Hampton from J. L. Goodwin about securing and cutting wood; Statement of total timber maintenance to forestry accounts in 1941; Questionnaire concerning Hardwood Cordwood for fuel dealers, operators and farmers, retail yards or other retailers; Permit for Cutting Wood, and registration of prospective purchasers; Statement from the Office of Price Administration of the Price Order for Firewood.
  - Maine and Son, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    Correspondence relating to the Sale of payment of Wood sold by H. Maine.
  - Maintenance Accounts, 1941-1942 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    Comparative Statement of Maintenance Accounts for Pine Acres Farm, January 1, to June 30, 1940-1941-1942.
  - Markets For Wood, 1926-1928, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    List of Lumber Manufacturers of Eastern Connecticut.
  - Meetings-Miscellaneous, Connecticut Forest and Park Association, 1927-1930-1933, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    A report to the Directors of the Connecticut Forestry Association; "Resolution Adopted at the 18th Annual Meeting of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States on Forestry"; George Washington Bi-Centennial Tree Planting"; Austin F. Hawes, State Forester, asking J. L. Goodwin to serve on the committee for the George Washington Bi-Centennial Tree Planting Celebration.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1922-1935 (Box 18, Folder 23)
    Discussions between J. L. Goodwin, and Captain J. H. Gibbons about surveying and diverting the Booth Road in Avon, Connecticut, on Talcott Mountain; Shipments of Wood from J. L. Goodwin to Graves and Strang, Incorporated, Coal, Coke and Wood.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1924-1941 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    Bills due to Mrs. Charles Farnham from J. L. Goodwin for rent, furniture, and dairy products; Sale of land to Mr. Edwin W. Fogg, and the paymant of interest and principal to J. L. Goodwin.
  - North Eastern Lumber Manufacturer's Report, 1933-1934 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    Report from the North Eastern Lumber Manufacturers relating to Code of Fair Competition for the Lumber and Timber Products Industries; Hardwood Inspection Agreement to Hardwood Operators; Amendments to the Code of Fair Competition for the Lumber and Timber Products Industries; Rules of Forest Practice and the Preamble.
  - Old Inventories, 1940-1947 (Box 18, Folder 26)
    Inventories of Pine Acres Farm, 1940-1942, 1947.
  - Orchards, 1918-1947 (Box 18, Folder 27)
    Orders to C. W. Atwater and Son for Apple Trees; James A. Newland, Director, State Chemist, The Newland Sanitary Labortory, Hartford, reporting samples of vinegar submitted for examinations to J. L. Goodwin; Statements for Orchard No. 1, relating to Orchard fertilizer used on farm for years, 1919-1934; Orchard No. 2, Pine Acres, 1922-1935; No. 3, 1925-1935; No. 4, 1931-1935; Valuation of the four orchards; Statements pertaining of Orchard Expense.
  - P, 1940 (Box 18, Folder 28)
    An agreement with Frank A. Phillips relating to selling and buying Cordwood; Correspondence with Arthur E. Pearl, Contractor, concerning work done on farm and the Guild House; Payroll Auditor's Reports from Hartford Accident and Indemnity Company; United States Social Security Act; R. F. Montgomery, Assistant, Secretary, The Phoenix Insurance Company corresponding with J. L. Goodwin with respect to a claim.
  - P, 1920-1941 (Box 18, Folder 29)
    Certificate from the Royal Insurance Company of Providence, Rhode Island, regarding Marion D. Pickles dwelling situated in Hampton.
  - Payroll Compensation Insurance-Farm Bureau Mutual Automobile Insurance Company, 1944-1947 (Box 18, Folder 30)
    Workmen's Compensation Policy; Statements pertaining to Premium due on Workmen's Compensation Insurance on Pine Acres Farm; Claim reports for employees who were injured on job; Summary of Man Labor Hours, Pine Acres Farm, 1944; Correspondence about accidents of farm employees; Workmens Compensation Insurance; Statements of Doctor Bills and Hospital Bills.
  - Pine Acres Farm Employees Trust Fund, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 31)
    Quarterly Statement-Wages Earned for September 30, 1943-December 15, 1943; Quarterly Statement-Victory Tax, March 31, 1943-June 15, 1943.
  - Pine Acres Farm, Martin Martino, 1929-1938 (Box 18, Folder 32)